Have you ever heard of beta amalloid?
It's not a planet the Voyager visits in
Star Trek. It's a protein that causes
massive issues in our brain. So much so
it leads to neurodeeneration
like the various forms of dementia like
Alzheimer's disease. Now our brain
slowly dies and sometimes quite rapidly
relatively speaking. So how can we stop
beta amalloid? Your body actually
already does naturally using something
called the glimpmphatic system. But
could dysfunction in your lymphatic
system be massively accelerating your
risk of Alzheimer's disease? And if so,
what can you do to save your brain? I'd
like to show you a few studies that
answer those questions. So, you may have
heard of this lymphatic system before,
and that's the one that when you're sick
can create enlarged lymph nodes in your
neck and arms. But that's not what we're
discussing here. We're discussing its
sibling system, the glimpmphatic system,
which is in our brain. Now, it's an
intricate mechanism where cells in your
brain create another pipe network around
your blood vessels going into our brain.
Think of it like a pipe within a pipe.
The smaller pipe is your artery or vein,
and the larger pipe is part of this
lymphatic system. It's made up of cells
that extend projections called nt and
create a barrier between your blood and
the actual brain cells. The space
between the first pipe, so your blood
vessel, and the second pipe, the nt is
called the pervascular space or PVS.
This is important to what I'm going to
be telling you. So keep the PVS sharply
in your mind. So fluid will travel from
the PVS pass through the NFTt and into
the space occupied by the main cells of
your brain like the neurons the cells
that you know actually communicate with
one another allowing us to think,
comprehend, breathe, move and literally
everything else that keeps us alive and
well. Exactly here is where beta
amalloid, a protein secreted by our
neurons and other cells, is found. It's
here between all these cells that beta
amalloid aggregates which means that it
clumps up together. Think of them like
bogs in the water between cells
disrupting communication between
neurons. Fortunately, as I alluded, the
liquid that comes from the PVS into this
space between the cells will pick up the
beta amalloid like a trash service and
carry it out of the brain going back
through the PVS on the outflow side.
This is as literal a brain cleaning as
we can get. And I have to pause here to
ask you how freaking cool is that. So in
simple terms, the fluid in your brain
washes away beta amalloid through this
pervascular plumbing system. That's the
main point. Knowing that what happens
when these pervascular spaces are
stressed or disrupted somehow for that
when we lean on studies that try to
investigate that question. When we I
mean scientists, humanity as a whole
look at the relationship of damaged or
dysfunctional pervascular space meaning
that there's not as tight of a barrier
between the end or there's a buildup of
proteins like amaloid that can't be
cleared out or the veins have stiffened
or any number of other reasons. The
point being they're not functioning like
they should. So what happens when we
stratify people based on clinically
independently repeatedly assessed PVS
health. So stage one being the
healthiest up to stage four being the
most disrupted. We can see that what
happens here. The vertical axis is the
risk of dementia. So that's the brain
disorder. So the higher up the better.
You are dementi free. The horizontal
axis is the time that these people have
been tracked and measured. each category
with four being the worst PBS health is
listed and then there are three graphs.
Those correspond to the different
regions of the brain. Now I'm not going
to complicate that aspect. The main
thing that you should see here is that
if the lines go down faster, there's
increased risk of dementia. And
certainly in the extremes, but largely
in a step-wise fashion, the worse your
PVS health, the greater the risk of
dementia. So the point here being that
if your pervascular space is disrupted
somehow there's a greater risk of
developing dementia like Alzheimer's
disease. Now in fact by some measures as
much as a 400% increased risk. So
something to really take seriously. Okay
fair enough. We see this association and
the researchers did adjust for a variety
of other factors that could account for
this association. Now, why exactly do we
see this relationship to dementia? On
one hand, it might seem obvious
considering that we've been over what we
just went over with beta amalloid
situation, but it's really not that
simple. For one, we can certainly turn
to other studies like these where the
direct relationship between the
lymphatic system and beta amalloid
plaque is assessed. These studies
looking at imaging of the brain are able
to tease out if amalloid plaques are
being evacuated from the brain
effectively. Essentially they show that
a better functioning lymphatic system is
linked to reduce beta amalloid in the
brain. And when looking at Alzheimer's
disease risk as opposed to all dementia
risk remember Alzheimer's is a specific
disease within the umbrella of dementia
we see concerning trend. The vertical
axis indicates an index of lymphatic
function. The higher the better. So the
three conditions listed are cognitively
normal individuals mild cognitive
impairment and Alzheimer's disease. When
we compare, there seems to be an almost
a step-wise link between lower lymphatic
function and worse brain health,
especially with Alzheimer's disease. But
more telling and counterintuitively
possibly, not all dementia related
proteins like beta amalloid show a
relationship with worse glimpmphatic
function. For example, another
implicated protein in Alzheimer's
disease is tow protein. The reason this
might not track with lymphatic function
is because Tao is an intracellular
protein. It's found inside the cells and
can't be washed away like beta amalloid.
Ultimately, the takeaway here is that
lymphatic function is related to beta
amalloid accumulation and Alzheimer's
disease. However, there are ways of
improving lymphatic function. This isn't
like a foregone conclusion that you will
develop Alzheimer's right on schedule.
I'd like to detail some of those factors
and some of the studies showing what we
can do to improve dementia risk
including Alzheimer's disease. One of
those factors is sleep, of course, and
I'll be getting into that in just a
minute. But in addition to that, there's
a fascinating study on sleeping position
and its impact on the lymphatic system.
Now, I'm covering that in the extended
version of this video that you're
watching, as well as some of the more
details on each of the studies that
we've covered up to this point. If
you're interested in checking it out,
then check out the Physiotic Insiders
membership. It comes uh with articles
for all my videos if you prefer to read.
Oh, and simple uh summaries for
highlights plus all these perks right
here like the private podcast, live
sessions, the community, and more.
Anyway, if you're interested in complete
access, check it out. Link is in the
description. So, what can be done to
prevent dementia and support our
lymphatic system? Well, one clinical
trial aimed to find out if we can have a
measurable impact through lifestyle
modification. So, when lifestyle
modification was implemented over 2
years, people in their 60s and 70s
experienced improvements in their
cognitive ability. The higher the lines
go, the better their cognitive function.
The red line is the people using
lifestyle improvements. So, what kind of
lifestyle interventions are we talking
about here? Well, four pillars. Here
they are. One, nutrition. So focused on
fruits and vegetables, but also
including some dairy and meat and eating
fish twice per week. So think of it
similar, but maybe not identical to a
Mediterranean style diet. Two, exercise.
So including strength training one to
three times per week. Uh plus two to
five times per week of endurance
training. Three, cognitive training. So
using a computer-based training like
puzzles, memory tasks for only 10 to 15
minutes per day. and even just like
three times per week. Four, vascular
risk management. Getting regular blood
tests for cholesterol, blood sugar,
testing your blood pressure, weight, and
generally keeping an eye on vascular
dementia related biomarkers, which are
the ones we just went over. So yes, a
well- balanced lifestyle directly
improves brain function, though we don't
know if this targets the lymphatic
system directly. So what evidence is
there of direct targeting? The answer is
sleep. There are some big influential
studies and some corroborative evidence
in humans that sleep is probably the
biggest player in maintaining a low
amaloid plaque levels in supporting the
lymphatic system. Importantly, the
quality of the sleep matters and the
stages of sleep. For example, getting
deep sleep, also known as slow wave
sleep, has been shown to have a specific
drastic effect at improving lymphatic
drainage. One quick tip is that pops up
in the research, though I'd like to make
some more specific content on this, is
the temperature. If you're
environmental, so your bedroom
temperature is between 19 and 21° C,
that's about like 66 and 70 in
Fahrenheit. It pro it promotes more deep
sleep and generally better highquality
sleep as a whole. So all this
considered, where does this land us?
Well, for one, while we've been going
over studies relating lymphatic function
to Alzheimer's disease, there's more
research that's needed to really nail
down the causitive connection. But based
on what we have now, there's certainly a
relationship there. And mechanistically,
it does make sense. You can reduce your
risk of dementia as a whole by improving
your nutrition, regular exercise, mental
training, and keeping a regular regular
eye on your risk factors for vascular
dementia like blood pressure and
cholesterol levels to just name two.
Otherwise, for targeting the lymphatic
system directly and likely all forms of
dementia, including Alzheimer's disease,
focus on sleep. It is among the most
important factors. So, sleep length is
one aspect. trying to get at least seven
hours. Then sleep quality by sleeping
through the night as well as possible,
but also entering slow wave sleep or
deep sleep. That's helped by things like
room temperature, keeping your room
between uh 19 and 21° C, that's 66 to
around 70° F. And there are many factors
that come into play for Alzheimer's and
dementia altogether. If you're
interested in a more complete story
beyond the glimpmphatic system, check
this video out. Thanks for tuning in.
I'll catch you in the next one.